Guide to the Association for Case Teaching Records
Yale University Divinity School Library
Association for Case Teaching records
1972-2014
RG 245
Yale University Divinity School Library
8
(19 boxes)
The Association for Case Teaching was established in 1978 to promote the use of case studies for improving the quality of theological teaching. The "case method" is a means of participatory and dialogical teaching and learning by group discussion of actual events. ACT was a professional association of college and seminary faculty members, pastors, denominational and ecumenical staff persons, lay leaders, church professionals and other interested persons who utilized the methodology of "case teaching" in their educational and training roles. Its membership included individuals and institutions from throughout the U.S., Canada, Europe, Africa and Asia.
Association for Case Teaching
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Association for Case Teaching, 2011; Gift of Robert and Alice Frazer Evans, 2016
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
First introduced into theological education in the 1960s, the case teaching method was used initially by only a very limited number of professors. It was the catalyst that helped generate a new focus on the power of teaching and learning in theological education. The result of this process was a series of 50 workshops that were conducted for theological seminaries in North America to provide an opportunity for faculty to think about the ways they were engaged in the pedagogical process of the preparation for ministry.
In 1971, the Association of Theological Schools (ATS), with the financial support of the Sealtantic Fund, established the Case Study Institute (CSI), a three-week long training program held each summer in Cambridge, Massachusetts, with a focus on adapting the legal and business school case approach to theological education. This was the first of six institutes held at Episcopal Divinity School under the sponsorship of the ATS and the Boston Theological Institute with a grant from the Sealantic Fund. Faculty and cases for this first institute were drawn primarily from the Harvard Business School.
During the next five years, over one hundred fifty theological professors from the United States and Canada, representing a broad variety of theological disciplines, attended the Institute. Many became staff members of subsequent institutes and almost all contributed their writing skills to develop a body of nearly two hundred theological cases. In 1977 Louis Weeks, with the support of the Intercollegiate Case Clearing House in Cambridge and ATS, compiled the first bibliography of theological cases.
The Association for Case Teaching (ACT) was formed in 1978 by a group of graduates of the CSI. Invitations were extended to college and university faculty, parish clergy, and lay leaders to join seminary faculty as participants. This new constituency broadened the scope of the institute and enriched the variety of cases being written.
Between 1978 and 1990 the annual summer institutes were sponsored by ACT in conjunction with Fuller, Southeastern Baptist Theological Seminary, Garrett Evangelical Seminary, and Toronto School of Theology. ACT has sponsored additional case workshops in Africa, Asia, Australia, Europe, and Latin America. Through the support of annual workshops for university seminary faculty, plus seminars and publications, ACT provided educational resources to strengthen pedagogical skills and to make the teaching of social science theory more applicable to life experiences. A Case Clearinghouse, co-sponsored by ACT and the Yale Divinity School Library, compiled around one thousand cases written since 1971.
In 1988 the collection was moved from the offices of ATS to Yale University Divinity School Library, where a staff implemented case distribution and began the task of entering the cases and the bibliography on computer discs. Yale librarian Steve Peterson was instrumental in the design and development of the first volume of the Journal for Case Teaching, one of the first professional journals that focused primarily on teaching in theological education.
ACT has equipped more than 1,600 persons in theological education in intensive and short-term workshops in the use of this dialogical method. ACT helped generate over 2,000 case studies in a variety of fields and more than 30 casebooks. The method has been shared with virtually every major association of theological schools in Africa, Asia, and Australia. There are networks of theological faculty members who have worked together to specifically expand and utilize the methodology for seminaries and congregations, especially in India, Australia, Indonesia, and South Africa.
During the twenty plus years of the association, there were more than 500 individual members and more than 100 institutional members including many of the theological seminaries in North America. The methodology is also used in universities and colleges, with chaplaincies, and in denominations and congregations in North America.
In the 1990s mediation and negotiation trainers in South Africa participating in the Empowering for Justice Reconciliation project adapted the case approach to their training in community conflict resolution. Rather than using cases written from a North American or wider African context, the trainers began writing cases that came directly from South African communities. They found that the process of objective analysis and group discussion of alternatives was particularly useful in racially and economically heterogeneous groups because it honed listening skills and broadened cultural understanding. With the application of the case teaching method to the South African model, the chapter on using cases in teaching conflict resolution began to be written.
More recently, a consortium of four schools, acting as institutional hosts for ACT, served as an important reflection of both the strength, growth, and diversity of the utilization of the pedagogical approach to enhancing the quality of teaching and learning in theological education. Yale Divinity School served ACT by archiving institutional records and collecting and distributing cases. San Francisco Theological Seminary and Golden Gate Baptist Seminary coordinated the Summer Institute and Advance Workshop. Finally, Abilene Christian University accepted the role to be the institutional site base for administrative purposes.
The ACT is no longer an active organization.
Scope and Contents
This collection provides documentation of the activities of the Association for Case Teaching from its establishment in the 1970s through the early 2000s when it ceased to be an active organization.
Activities of the Association for Case Teaching included publishing a journal, a periodic newsletter and maintaining a case bibliography, sponsoring one or more teaching institutes a year, reviewing and selecting new case studies for inclusion in the permanent case collection, and providing assistance with case information and selection.
Added in 2017, Series VI contains correspondence and documentation donated by long time Executive Co-Directors Alice Fraser Evans and Robert Evans.
Arrangement
I. Membership Records
II. Organization and Policy Records
III. Workshops and Institutes
IV. Publications
V. ACT Distributed Materials
VI. Addendum: Files Received from Executive Directors
Theology -- Case studies
- Membership, 1972-1999; Series I
  - Membership (1972-74) Map (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Membership List, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Membership List, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Membership List, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Membership List, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Membership List, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Membership List, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Membership List, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Membership List, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Membership List, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Membership List, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Membership List, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Membership List, 1997-8 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Membership List, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Organization & Policy Records, 1978-2001; Series II
  - Administrative
    - One Page Organization Summary (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Officers and Minutes, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Officers and Minutes, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Officers and Minutes, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Officers and Minutes, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Officers and Minutes, 1984-5 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Officers and Minutes, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Officers and Minutes, 1987-8 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Officers and Minutes, 1989-90 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Officers and Minutes, 1991-93 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Officers and Minutes, 1994-5 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Officers and Minutes, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Officers and Minutes, 1997-8 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Officers and Minutes, Correspondence, including regarding dissolution of ACT, 1999-2014 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Incorporation and 1st biennial report (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - By-Laws (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Sub-committee on Planning and Evaluation, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Responsibilities of the ACT Co-directors; Future Search Conference - Discovering a Renewed Future for the ACT, June 19-21, 1998, Washington, DC (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Responsibilities of the ACT Leadership Team, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - End of ATS Case Study Project (Gail Chambers report), 1988 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Relationship with Columbia Seminary (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - ACT/YDS proposal (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Financial Records
    - Tax Documents (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Financial Statements, 1981-1990 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Record of Funds, 1986-1989 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Institute Budgets and Expenses, 1991-1998 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Newsletter Expenses, 1980-1989 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - General Expenses, 1995-1998 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Wabash Funding & Program Report, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Lilly Foundation Grant Application, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Workshops and Institutes, 1972-2000; Series III
  - Event Photos (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Summer Institute Fellows, 1972-1977 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Case Method Institute Workshop, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Case Method Institute Workshop, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Case Method Institute Workshop, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Case Method Institute Workshop, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Case Method Institute Workshop, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Case Teaching Workshop, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Summer Workshops, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Summer Workshops, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Summer Workshops, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Summer Workshops, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Summer Institute, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Summer Institute, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Case Teaching Workshop, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Summer Institute, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Summer Institute, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Case Method Workshop, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Summer Institute, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Summer Institute, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Summer Institute, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Summer Institute, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Summer Institute, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - ACT Future Search Conference, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Summer Institute, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Publications, 1983-2001; Series IV
  - Case Studies
    - Listing of case studies with bibliographic information (see also http://divinity-adhoc.library.yale.edu/Resources/caseassn.htm) (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - 1858, A - Ab (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Scope and Contents
      1858 prayer revival Abelard, Bernard, and the council of sens (a) Abelard, Bernard, and the council of sens (b) Aberdeen heresy: Professor Smith and the Pentateuchal problem Abortion study committee Abraham Lincoln and American civil religion
    - Ab - Ad (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Abraham Lincoln and American civil religion Abstinence or temperance: decision before slate river presbytery Acceptance: Jai Chandra's diary The added committee Advent Sunday sermon "Adventures with the American Legion"
    - Af - Aj (Box 4, Folder 4)
      Affirmative action? Affirmation of Life After the riot at Renton prison Agenbit of Inwit Ahaz of Judah Aids protection -- for whom? Ajax electronics co., Inc. (a) Ajax electronics co., Inc. (b)
    - Al (Box 4, Folder 5)
      Alexander Petersen Alfred North Whitehead Ali Miller leaves the Y All alone All Hallow's Printery
    - An (Box 4, Folder 6)
      An(other) American family Anderson and the Sheraton community organization Andre Dumont (a) Andre Dumont (b) Anne Hutchinson and the antinomian controversy Anne Hutchinson and the Puritans of Massachusetts Bay Colony
    - Ar - As (Box 4, Folder 7)
      Archbishop challenges the Church Archbishop's mansion Aristotle As we have forgiven Asahel Nettleton and the Emergence of the Finney Revivals Asia Resources, Inc. Associates Dilemma
    - Ay - Bar (Box 4, Folder 8)
      Ayuda? Help Baby boy Hernandez Bake sale Banjos or Bach? Baptism of Jonathan Cutrone Baptism of Michael Barman declaration (a) Barmen declaration (b)
    - Bat - Be (Box 4, Folder 9)
      Battle of the building blues Bay city public library Because wisdom can't be told Being legal in Ames Belgian authority v. Morrison and Sheppard Ben Chavis case Ben Phillips dies, funeral today Berengar of Tours and the second Eucharistic controversy Bert Johnson Beyond the Battle
    - Bil - Bir (Box 4, Folder 10)
      Bill and Alicia (A) Bill and Alicia (B) Bill Franklin, the gay wedding, and the bishop (b) Bill Johnson: pastoral supervisor Bill Underwood Bill Waldman Billy Graham and worldwide evangelization Birds over Zimbabwe
    - Bis - Bo (Box 4, Folder 11)
      Bishop Pike Black Jesus Blessed are the peacemakers Blessed are those who mourn (a) Blessed are those who mourn (b) Bob Clark and the previous life reading (a) Bob Clark and the previous life reading (b) Bob Clark and the previous life reading (c) Bonny's blues Boy Scouts and Pentecost
    - Br - Cal (Box 4, Folder 12)
      Bread for the world Build your church here But Christ isn't here today By the Sword The Call Call and job hunt of Anne Montgomery Call to a Strange Land Calvary at the Crossroads Calvary Church Calvin and the Italian anti-Trinitarians (a) & (b)
    - Cam - Car (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Camden college and tenure Camilo Garcia, the cardinal, and the bank workers' strike Can a woman lead the church? Can Mrs. Rose C. teach the junior girls Sunday school class? Cancun The Canterbury trail Captain Barnes Captain Billy Bright Captain Rip Chord Carl Phillips was fired Carlos and Al
    - Case (An - Bi) (Box 5, Folder 2)
      The case of Anselm and Aquinas The case of the Apostles' Creed The case of Aristotle The case of Augustine Case of Bishop Hooper
    - Case (Bl - Ha) (Box 5, Folder 3)
      Case of Blaise Pascal The case of the Confession of 1967 The case of Descartes Case of the gambling pastor The Case of Harmonious Discord
    - Case (He - John) (Box 5, Folder 4)
      The case of the Heidelberg catechism The case of Hume The case of James Case of John Henry Newman (1801-90) Case of John Wesley
    - Case (Jon - Many) (Box 5, Folder 5)
      Case of Jonathan Edwards (1703-58) The case of Kant The case of Kierkegaard A case of many numbers
    - Case (Marx - Ni) (Box 5, Folder 6)
      The case of Marx Case of Miguel Hidalgo y costilla (1753-1811) and of Jose Maria Morelos y pavan (1765-1815) The case of the moderator's conference on the unity of the church The case of the Nicene Creed
    - Case (P - Soc) (Box 5, Folder 7)
      Case of the pistol-packing preacher The case of the Scots confession The case of the Second Helvetic Confession The case of Socrates
    - Case (Sor - West) (Box 5, Folder 8)
      Case of Soren Aabye Kierkegaard (1813-55) The case of Susan B. Anthony Case of the Uganda martyrs (1885-86) The case of the Westminster confession of faith and catechisms
    - Case (White - Wit) (Box 5, Folder 9)
      The case of Whitehead Case of William Edward Burghardt Dubois (1868-1963) The case of Wittgenstein
    - Cat - Chi (Box 5, Folder 10)
      Cats and coons Center city ministry Central area council-- b.s.a. (a) Central area council--b.s.a. (b) Changing the Face of the Parish Charismatics at Westminster Charles Chauncy and new world concerns China and the church
    - Cho - Christo (Box 5, Folder 11)
      Choice between death and...(a), (b), & (c) Chris Ripley (a), (b), & (c) A Christian soldier Christianity: a Jewish sect or a worldwide community of faith Christological councils (a), (b), (c),& (d)
    - Christus - Church (Box 6, Folder 1)
      Christus victor: Gustaf Aulen on atonement Church and modern industry (a) & (b) Church and the second sex Church and social problems The church at the crossroads I The church at the crossroads II A Church for all people
    - Churchless - Communication (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Churchless child Circle Church and the teachers' strike City of gold Closing the crypt Cokes and pretzels in the Lord's Supper Colleagues of Cecile Colonel Davis "Come, Holy Spirit(s)" Commitment for Larry Adams Communication: Jai Chandra's diary (4)
    - Community - Con (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Community center (a) & (b) Community of Christ the servant Conflict management Conflicting Loyalties Confrontation at Marburg Constant in prayer Consternation at Cactus Church
    - Cor - Cov (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Corporate policy Costly choice Cotton Mather and the Salem Witch Trials Could I have done more? Covenant keeping Covington Hills Church
    - Cro - Dan (Box 6, Folder 5)
      Crossfire baptism (a) & (b) Crossroads Cues for James Millman Daily, daily sing the praises Dance of life A Dane with the Danes Dante Cavallo
    - Dav - Daw (Box 6, Folder 6)
      David Namer: an interview with a professional salesman Davis case Davis regional medical center Dawson's (tv and appliances), Inc.
    - De - Del (Box 6, Folder 7)
      De trinitate Deadline: March 14 Dean Confident (a) Dean Confident (b) Dear Aunt Sarah Death of Fanny Grimes Death of the rector Deborah, Toby, and the confirmation class (a) & (b) Delicate and difficult matter (a) & (b)
    - Den - Do (Box 6, Folder 8)
      "Denied – Bad Credit" Derbyville United Methodist Church Development of income property: "interim loans" Dexter paper Dialogue partner Dick Shannon DMin Dilemma Do my child "Don't come over and help us!" "Do we need a new pastor?"
    - Dor - Dr (Box 6, Folder 9)
      Dorothy moves into feminism Down in the Valley Doug and Mike Doug Carter and the Wilkinson's (a), (b), (c) & (d) Dr. Bowman on the issue of abortion Dr. Crawford's plight The Dream Job
    - Ea - Em (Box 6, Folder 10)
      Early Nation Easter controversy Easter sunrise Ecclesiastical council Ecclesiastical equality for women Echoes: family planning in an extended family Eco-control systems, Inc. El Salvador and the cost of Christian witness Elective death Eli black story The emergence of Pentecostalism
    - En - Ex (Box 6, Folder 11)
      English Spoken Here Enshrined Episcopal diocese of Arkansas Esso pappas in thessaloniki Evangelical theological seminary (a) & (b) Evangelism explosion on trial "Explosive Hospitality"
    - Ey - Fish (Box 6, Folder 12)
      Eye of the needle The faith of Granville Stanley Hall Familyhood of God Farm workers of Rhodesia Farmington Presbyterian Church Felix Dupanloup and the dogma of infallibility Fire the Minister? Fishermen, Inc.
    - First - For (Box 7, Folder 1)
      First Baptist Church of Middletown First Lutheran Church Fisher Foods, Inc. For all people For better, for worse (a), (b), & (c) For the life of the church For the love of money
    - Forgive - Ge (Box 7, Folder 2)
      Forgiveness? The fortunate illness Free for--free from Freedom to grow From exodus to exile From Freud to Masters and Johnson: the feminine psychology of Helene Deutsch Funeral for Noriko-San Gail Marie Ryan, r.n. George and Marion Getting away from it all (a) and (b)
    - Gi - Gol (Box 7, Folder 3)
      The Gift of a Broken Body Gift of healing Gift organ Give us this day our daily bread Giving thanks Global village-living God and Shockley at Yale God is testing us Golden eagles (a), (b), (c), (d), & (e)
    - Gom - Gre (Box 7, Folder 4)
      Gomer's side of the story Good Morning, Sarah Gospel agenda in a global context The gospel, a rock, and a hard place Grace Baptist Church Great train robbery (a) & (b) Green pastures Greg Wright and Twin Rivers Presbytery (a) & (b)
    - Ha - He (Box 7, Folder 5)
      Harper's retreat Has the church anything to say? Having a wonderful time Hastings Image Healey and Jensen Grocer Co. The Healthy Christian Life Henry powers (a) & (b) Heresy dilemma Heresy of John McLeod Campbell
    - Hi - Hom (Box 7, Folder 6)
      Hidden budget His first death His first parish (a), (b), & (c) Holts, their kids, and mama A home for chad
    - How - Hur (Box 7, Folder 7)
      How can we answer this letter? Howard Palmer (a) & (b) The hub Hurricane Agnes
    - I (Box 7, Folder 8)
      I am your friend I can keep quiet no longer I like the way you walk I want to be a priest I want to come home I was a stranger I was in prison I will go to the altar of god
    - Id- In (Box 7, Folder 9)
      I'd like to lodge a complaint Ignatius Thophorus, bishop of Antioch Igo & Green Illinois investors insurance (a) Illinois investors insurance (b) In sickness and in health In the eyes of the Lord
    - Ina - Is (Box 7, Folder 10)
      Inadequacies: Jai Chandra's diary (2) Initiation The interchurch world movement Inter-Varsity Christian Fellowship Irene Is suicide a sin? Is this for me?
    - Isa - Jai (Box 8, Folder 1)
      Isaac Backus and the Separation of Church and State Jack Mullin, minister Jai Chandra's diary: an unreported account of the strivings of a field worker (1-6)
    - Jak - Jes (Box 8, Folder 2)
      Jakub's Wake-up Call James Cardinal Gibbons and the Americanization of the Catholic Church James Towers: the missing degree A Javanese Teacher Jenny Rogers Jerry Janus Jesus doesn't love you when you're naughty Jesus people
    - Ji - John Lewis (Box 8, Folder 3)
      Jim and Nancy Swazey (a) & (b) Jimmie Barton John and Barbara Adams John and Matilda Fee: return to Berea? (a) & (b) John Courtney Murray, the American experience and religious freedom at Vatican II John Franklin Petet John Howard Yoder and homogenous unit principle John Lewis--MBA
    - John Lindbeck - John Scopes (Box 8, Folder 4)
      John Lindbeck John Parker: "freedom how?" (a)& (b) John Quincy Adams and the Spanish slave mutiny John Scopes and the debate over evolution
    - John Woolman - Jon (Box 8, Folder 5)
      John Woolman and American slavery Johnstown department of purchase Jonathan Edwards and the Great Awakening
    - Jou - La (Box 8, Folder 6)
      Journey into a Little Known Country June Sanborn (a), (b), & (c) Just a Matter of Time Justice for whom? Kentucky revival Kenyon case Kimbanguist membership in the World Council of Churches King's temple La huelga --California farm workers' strike (a), (b) & (c)
    - Lau - Let's (Box 8, Folder 7)
      Lausanne congress Law #514 Law and Order and Apocalyptic Scripture Leaven in the loaf Lee Larson Let the People Go Let us break bread together Let Us In Let's close the Sunday school
    - Letter - L'Op (Box 8, Folder 8)
      The letter Letters (a) & (b) Lil and Henry (a), (b), & (c) Lisa's disappearance Live or let die Lock-in L'Operation Emmaus
    - Lor - Maria (Box 8, Folder 9)
      The Lord's Supper Turned Into Disaster: The So-Called Antioch Incident Luther, Carlstadt and Protestant reform Lyman Beecher (1775-1863) Lyman Beecher: Calvinist Orthodoxy and the New Theology Machen and the Modernist Movement Making it: the easy way The man born blind (john 9) Maria Rodriguez
    - Mark - Martyr (Box 8, Folder 10)